DYING IS EASY, COMEDY IS HARD

Dan Simmons & Edward Bryant

Seeing Johnny Carson rip off his own face, just like one of those effects in an early David Cronenberg movie, was bad enough. But what came next was truly grotesque.

I gotta admit, I stared. But then we all had to be an appreciative audience—the goons with Uzis and MAC-10s, and H&K miniguns made sure of that. If you’re wondering how I know so much about all that cool ordnance, it’s not ’cause I spend a lot of time on the street—it’s because I see a lot of B-movies.

I really hope I live to go to a lot more . . .

The Aladdin Theater is named sifter the dude that rubbed a lamp and got a genie. Right now I wish I had the three wishes that guy received. All of us here on the stage do. No genie coming out tonight. Nope, just pain, blood, and a whole lot of grief.

Frankly, it’s enough to make me rethink my career . . .

I admit it, I come alive—truly alive—only at night. Then I descend on the concrete canyons and brick catacombs of Gotham City, take the train into its decaying downtown between Art Deco skyscrapers from some earlier age, walk its rainswept streets and ratty back alleys smelling of garbage and the homeless, seek out its basement improv clubs and East Side nightclubs sandwiched in between the porno palaces and hotsheet hotels—the clubs smelling of cigars and cheap perfume and urine and something much worse: flop sweat—and then, only then, in the dark belly of this dying city, performing for the drunks and adulterers and lost souls and lonely insomniacs, then I come alive. Then—in the dark, with the bile of fear burning at my insides and the stench of failure and humiliation just a short arc of silence away—then my true life begins.

I know now that I’m not alone. There are others who come alive at night, in the back alleys of Gotham City. Others who wait through the mundane turning of days for the violent whirl of night’s greatest realities. Others who shed their daylight skins and become other people. I know that now.

The creature that calls himself the Joker is one. The Batman—that human puzzle wrapped in a cowl and enigma—is another. I know that now.

And I almost understand.

This isn’t going well. Where to start?

My name is Pete Tulley. I’m twenty-nine years old, black—or African-American as the self-appointed spokespersons of our race now say, not married, not living with anyone right now, and during the day I’m a manager of the Burger Biggie franchise on the comer of Sprang and Robinson. It’s not really that bad of a job. The hardest part is keeping a steady flow of kids trained and working behind the counter, getting them to understand that Burger Biggie is a job, a responsibility, and not just a place to hang out and laugh with their friends while the customer stands and waits for his Biggie and fries. I’m a graduate of Burger Biggie Hamburger College—the franchise’s four-week training school in Peoria, Illinois—and as stupid as that sounds, as easy as it is to sneer at the idea of a Hamburger College, the chain actually stands for something (even if that “something” is only good fast food, prepared promptly to nationwide standards of taste and quality of ingredients, in clean surroundings), and I try to communicate those standards to the people I train and manage. I must be at least partially successful at that since my Biggie at Sprang and Robinson has won the Gotham City metro-area B.B. Excellence and Cleanliness Award two years running.

And despite the obvious temptation—since stand-ups are like fiction writers in that they use everything around them—I’ve never done hamburger franchise jokes in my routines. It seems like too cheap a shot. Plus, I owe something to the people who keep me employed in the daytime so I can come alive at night.

But I’ll use the gags someday. In the long run, nothing is sacred.

I’ve been a stand-up comic for three years. Three years this March. Like most would-be comics, I started by getting a laugh from my family when I was a little kid. (I remember the first time—it was unintentional—I was six and watching a Dolly Parton special on TV and said, “I bet she can swim real good with those inflated things on her chest.” If we’d been alone that evening, my mother probably would have frowned and my dad would have swatted me on the side of the head, but we had Uncle Louis and Aunt Nell and Cousin Sook and a bunch of other folks over—they’d been drinking beer since the picnic that afternoon—and the room just howled with laughter. It became a sort of family joke—Uncle Louis used to mention it about everytime we got together—and it was really the first time I’d been noticed by everyone. Or at least the first time they’d all noticed me and liked me.)

Anyway, it taught me that sex gets laughs, and if you can throw in some popular culture or a public figure, so much the better.

I went to Charity Hills High School—although there were no hills in our old Southside suburb of Gotham and by the mid-seventies there was damned little charity either—and I became a comic there just to survive. Charity Hills had inherited most of the Gotham City gangs by then, sort of gang franchises, I guess you might say, and to stay an independent you had to be incredibly smart or damn tough. I was neither. So I made myself funny.

The caption under my high school yearbook photo says “Always good for a laugh” and that was my armor and chameleon cloak. I figured that the jocks and street goons and dopeheads and musclebound dipshits who ordinarily showed their superiority by beating up wimpy types like me would think twice if I had a reputation as a clown. I figured that it might be easier for them to laugh at me—make me perform for their peers in the hallways and gyms and cloakrooms of dear old CHHS rather than stomp the crap out of me. And it worked. Most of the time.

Anyway, I started taking comedy seriously a couple of years ago, after I realized that nothing else in my life was going to give me a life worth living. I started out in the suburban improv clubs, getting in on amateur nights where people came to laugh at us rather than with us. That was okay. I was used to it. I always threw up before a performance, but I soon began to judge audience response by whether I threw up after the show.

I spent a long, hungry summer out in the Los Angeles area, getting booked for very few performances of my own, but getting to see a lot of the greats in the field at their old comedy club stomping grounds. The field of amateurs was too rich for me to compete out there, so I came back to Gotham City—where at least I knew a few of the club owners, had done them favors and could get a few in return. And besides, Burger Biggie doesn’t have any franchises west of the Mississippi.

And so I came alive at night for two years and then some, taking the 10:38 p.m. train in from Finger Park to Gotham Center, performing for money when I could—usually at one of the East Side back-alley basement clubs, a place for the slum dwellers to come in out of the cold and for the yuppies and dinner-jacket types to go slumming—but usually I had to settle for another amateur night, another contest, or another free-drinks and dinner-if-you-get-here-early-enough performance.

I got to know most of the other comedy club circuit people. A few went on to the ranks of the serious professional. One got rich and famous and died snorting bad coke in Las Vegas last fall. Most got discouraged, dropped out, and have been replaced by younger would-be somebodies. A few, like me, have hung in there and taken what they could get—honing their material, slowly improving their performances and on-stage personalities, trying to make up in experience and sheer persistence what they lack in talent. A few of these other survivors of the Long March have become friends. Some of the rest are real assholes. All of them, friends and assholes alike, are competitors.

But in a strange way we are like some medieval guild: aging apprentices hoping to become journeymen and praying to be elevated to Master. We’re sort of a family of misfit hopefuls, sharing nothing but our common dream and the fact that we come alive only at night, in front of the audience.

And then the Joker started killing us.

It was last November in that gray, dead-branch period between the childlike nonsense of Halloween and the all-too-adult loneliness of Thanksgiving. The Carob Comedy Club on Alameda and Franklin had been staging a three-week Comedy Countdown—shows every Tuesday and Saturday—with a bunch of us eliminating each other via applause-o-meter showdown for a five-hundred-dollar first prize. That sounds like a decent amount until you realize that Al Jacobs, manager of the Carob, had over a dozen amateur comics firing off their best material twice a night, two times a week for three weeks, and only the winner would end up getting anything.

Anyway, it was the final Saturday night and the original mob of stand-ups had been winnowed down to seven—me, my cracker friend Boonie Sandhill, a tired old ex-borscht-belt comic named Dandy John Diamond, a Roseanne Barr imitation called Tiffany Strbynsky, a gifted black teenager named Fast Eddie Teck, a beautiful but not very funny medical student named Diana Mulhollen, and George Marlin. I’d drawn the first slot for the late show and the audience wasn’t just cold, it was frigid. I gave it my best shot—using my Cola Wars stuff where every major world event of the past three decades was explained as an incidental by-product of the global sales war between Coke and Pepsi—but either the material was too cerebral for this crowd or it just wasn’t my night. I knew I was out of the running even before I took my bows, reset the mike on the stand, and backed out of the spotlight. At least Tiffany waddled onstage to a warmer crowd.

Al Jacobs lets us early casualties sit at the bar and down a few comped drinks while we watch the others work. Tiffany was hot this night, but she still was only a good imitation of the real thing and even though the applause-o-meter swung almost half again as far to the right as it had for me, I knew that the race would be between Fast Eddie and George Marlin.

Marlin was next and he hit the audience hard and fast. New Jersey was overweight but he never did fat jokes; his dialect was so Brooklynesque that it made Boone Sandhill’s drawl sound normal, but Marlin didn’t rely on dialect or borough in-jokes. He rarely did the offcolor stuff that makes up ninety percent of club routines these days. George was just funny and he generally just schmoozed along with tales from his childhood and early adolescence that had the sense of this-really-happened, which every comedy bit needs and so few have.

So George was telling about his days as a lonely teenager and how he was convinced he was a superhero—the Dung Beetle, armored nemesis of evil-doers everywhere—and the audience was roaring and I was on my third vodka rocks and the applause-o-meter was pinning itself and I was wondering idly whether Fast Eddie’s street-smart vulgar strut’n’jive routine could top this stuff, when suddenly George stopped in midroutine and stared at the microphone in his hand.

The head of the mike was growing, inflating like a balloon. George stepped back, still holding the thing and watching it expand, and because Al Jacobs was too cheap to install cordless traveling mikes, George got tangled in the wire and glanced back to see what was stopping him. Meanwhile, the audience was still roaring, thinking—as I did for a second—that the expanding mike was part of the routine, some phallic gag.

In those final seconds, George knew it wasn’t part of the night’s entertainment; the head of the mike was a metal sphere and it had grown to the size of a soccer ball. Still tangled in the cord, George started to drop the microphone as if it were the business end of a snake.

The audience roared. The mike exploded in some sort of shaped charge, taking off most of George’s head and smearing the maroon curtains behind him with hair, blood, and brain matter.

Laughter is like an avalanche—slow to get started, but once its moving it has an inertia of its own. Even with the gasps and screams of shock, it took ten or fifteen seconds for the last waves of laughter to die out. Then, for a moment, there was silence except for a few sobs from a woman near the front.

George’s pear-shaped body had stood there for a second or two, headless, his fingers still curved around the mike he was in the process of dropping. Then the corpse fell forward and hit the boards with a sound I will never forget, arterial blood sprayed the closest tables, and the room was filled with chaos as everyone—myself included—stood, shouted, cried for help, or merely screamed. I remember that Diane Mulholland rushed from backstage and knelt next to George—the knees of her pantyhose wicked red from the blood. She looked offstage as if seeking help. Al Jacobs rushed onstage, froze as if he were physically incapable of coming closer to the corpse, and stood there, wringing his hands and grimacing.

I set down my drink and stood on the lowest rung of the barstool, just trying to see over the heads of the mindlessly surging crowd.

And then, a moment after the laughter ended and the shouts and sobs and cries of confusion began to ebb toward a more sinister silence, then the laughter began.

It was not quite laughter. It was more like the frenzied barking of a jackal or the amplified cough of a hyena than any sound of mirth I’d ever heard come from a human throat. And then the face appeared.

Ten feet tall, white-skinned and green-haired, teeth yellowed within the terrible rictus that passed for a grin, the giant head materialized and floated in midair above George’s body. If George’s corpse had remained standing, this bloated visage would have replaced his missing head like someone poking his face through a cardboard cutout at a boardwalk photo booth.

It took me a second to realize that I was looking at the Joker. Living in Gotham City most of my life, I’d seen news photographs and the rare snippets of videotape, but they had seemed unreal, cartoonlike, and this nightmare face floating above George’s corpse was all too real.

Diane screamed and flinched away from the apparition. Al Jacobs backed to the edge of the stage, teetered, and crouched, holding one arm above his bald head as if ready to ward off a blow.

The Joker laughed. The image seemed solid. I saw the pores in the white flesh, noticed the pink gums above yellow teeth, and watched as the wide eyes blinked in merriment and pure insanity. The laughter echoed off walls and curtains as patrons fled, shoving over tables in their haste to reach the fire exits. Diane Mulholland slumped unconscious in a pool of George’s blood.

The image of the Joker glanced down at her as if the projection could actually see, smiled, and lifted its long chin. It . . . he . . . was looking across the heads of the crowd directly at me.

“TUT, TUT, TUT,” came the amplified voice. I remember seeing Charles Manson interviewed once on Sixty Minutes. Manson’s voice sounded like Dan Rather’s compared to the black-ice tones I heard now. “I GUESS THIS FELLOW HAS NO HEAD FOR COMEDY!”

The crazy laughter rose in volume. Behind me I heard shouts at the front entrance, knew the cops had arrived, but I wasn’t able to turn away from that wild-eyed gaze.

“WELL, HE WON’T BE THE LAST TO GIVE HIS ALL TO LADY COMEDY,” echoed the mad voice. The image giggled, and then a strange transformation came over the face. It was as if rats were scurrying under the white cheesecloth of the Joker’s flesh. At first, I thought it might be a malfunction of the projector or whatever I was, but then I realized that it was the Joker’s actual features that were shifting, sliding into different pat terns, jerking like the expression of a doll in a clumsily made claymation cartoon.

The Joker was no longer smiling. His green had seemed to wave like seaweed in a strong current as he glared down at the last fleeing patrons, flicked a glance at the corpse, and then returned his gaze to me. “THERE IS ONLY ONE JOKER IN GOTHAM CITY.”

He was gone. The cops burst in, ran around, swung their revolvers in that self-conscious two-armed pose we see on TV every night, and shouted at each other over the din. Some stood around George’s corpse and looked as helpless as Al Jacobs had, while others rushed back stage, guns still drawn.

I knew they wouldn’t find the Joker. I lifted my glass and finished my drink. My hands were shaking so hare that I had to use both of them to get the glass to m; mouth without spilling the last of my vodka.

They kept us until almost four in the morning. I’d never been interrogated before and it wasn’t much like the movies. They didn’t grill me, they didn’t use the good cop, bad-cop routine, and nobody shone a bright light in my face. In fact, they interviewed us one at a time in the long, narrow storeroom in the back of Al’s club, and there was hardly enough light to see the two homicide detectives asking the questions. They sounded more tired than I was. One of them had a serious smoker’s cough and sucked on lozenges between cigarettes.

Mostly, it was boring. They went over everything twice, then a third time. Then they started again.

“Are you sure Mr. Marlin said nothing to you in the green room?” the cop with the cough asked.

I sighed and began to give the same answer I’d given them thrice before. Then a shadow in the comer behind them moved, detached itself from the darkness there, and glided toward us.

“Holy shit,” I whispered.

It was the Batman. I heard his cape rustle, caught a glimpse of the peaked points on the dark cowl, but mostly he blended into the darkness in that little room. Only his face and that weird emblem on his chest seemed to reflect light.

He glided forward until he loomed over me, wrinkles in that cape glinting like black silk where they glinted at all. The cops made room for him but said nothing. I couldn’t say anything at that moment.

I know, you live in Gotham City most of your life, you’re supposed to see the Batman all the time. Well, you don’t, any more than you chat with Dustin Hoffman a lot if you live in L.A. or lunch with Donald Trump if you hang around New York. Oh, you see photos in the paper every once in a while and I almost saw Batman at a dedication of a new community center in Charity Hills once when I was twelve . . . but my dad and I got stuck in traffic and when we got there he was gone. You live in Gotham, you take a sort of pride in being identified with the Bat Guy . . . sort of like San Francisco residents are proud of the Golden Gate Bridge . . . but you don’t see him. To tell the truth, it’d been so long since I’d even read about him, that I’d sort of forgotten he was real.

He was real enough now.

I sat back, tried to look cool, tried not to gulp visibly as this cowled face leaned forward, neck muscles all corded under black silk, tried to listen coolly rather than scream when that gloved hand touched my shoulder. I’m thin, average height, but no wimp. Still, I had the definite impression that his hand could pulverize my collarbone and shoulder just by giving a squeeze.

He didn’t squeeze.

“Mr. Tulley,” he said. His voice sounded soft, almost preoccupied. But I sure as hell wouldn’t want to get the owner of that voice angry. “Mr. Tulley, do you know any reason why someone . . . even the Joker . . . would want to kill George Marlin?”

“Uh-uh,” I said, always a snappy one with repartee.

I could see his eyes through slits in that midnight cowl. I’m pretty observant—stand-up comics have to be—but I have no idea what color they were.

“Mr. Tulley, is there anything that you haven’t mentioned which you think might help us with this investigation?”

“Uh-uh.” This time I managed to punctuate it by shaking my head.

The Batman nodded—more toward the two cops than at me—and then he took a step back and seemed to blend back into the shadows like black ink spilled on a dark velvet cloth.

The cop with the smoker’s cough led me to the door while I strained to keep from peering over my shoulder at the comer.

“Thanks, Mr. Tulley,” said the detective. I could smell the lozenge he was chewing on. “Go home and get some rest. We’ll call you if we need you, but I think this’ll be all.”

“Uh-huh,” I said, grateful to be leaving, grateful to be getting out of that little room.

But it wasn’t all. Not by a long shot.

Bruce appeared one day after the second murder.

It was three nights later, some of us were working the old Aladdin Dinner Theater, figuring that whoever was taking notes on comics for the joke-off would probably hit Aladdin’s traditional Tuesday Night Laugh Riot.

Somebody hit it all right.

The Aladdin is one of the great old movie palaces built during the early days of the Depression. It’s part Taj Mahal, part Pharaoh’s tomb, a bit of Baghdad, and a whole lot of old-movie fantasy. The place is gigantic, with two levels of balconies, box seats, red carpets, murals, and corridors like caverns out of an Indiana Jones movie: rococo ornamentation everywhere, bronze hands holding torches for lighting fixtures, dusty chandeliers—the whole bit. Aladdin’s had decayed to the point of being a downtown porno theater in the sixties, was converted to a disco during the seventies, was abandoned for a while, and then became a dinner theater cum nightclub during the mid-eighties.

The place was too big for comedy: the night Tiffany was murdered, there were almost as many of us waiting to go onstage as there were people in the audience. The rows of theater seats behind the tables were empty, the balconies were dark, and the private boxes were sealed off. The small lamps on the dozen tables near the stage shed little light. The place smelled of mildewed carpets, old cigars, and rot.

And flop sweat.

There was a plainclothes detective in the audience. Max Weber, Aladdin’s manager, had pointed him out. He didn’t need to. Anybody could have spotted the shiny black suit, paunch, clip-on holster, and white socks and made the old guy as a cop.

People weren’t laughing when Tiffany died. She was having a bad night; the Roseanne Barr material wasn’t working, there was a heckler down front whom she couldn’t out-nasty, and she was sweating heavily . . . obviously just trying to get through to the end of the routine. I was on last, still at least forty-five minutes to go after Fast Eddie and a couple of others, so I was having a drink at an empty table and feeling sorry for Tiffany.

Suddenly, in midpunchline, a glass box came sliding down on wires from the dark catwalks above and slammed onto the stage, enclosing Tiffany as surely as an entymologist’s plastic jar would trap a bug.

There was a click, the mike cord was severed, and Tiffany stumbled as some sort of bottom slid under her, sealing the glass box. It couldn’t be glass of course—I realized even then that it had to be some sort of plastic or Plexiglas—but it looked like a glass phone booth.

Tiffany screamed, but her shouts were made almost inaudible by the cage. The plainclothes cop stared a moment and then jumped to his feet, groping for the gun on his belt.

The Joker walked onstage, aimed his cane, and shot the cop. Actually, the head of the cane flew through the air, trailing a thin wire, and slammed into the cop’s chest. The fat detective spasmed and collapsed. We learned later that the cane had fired something called a taser . . . a sort of high-voltage stun weapon. It wasn’t designed to kill. The Joker couldn’t have known that the detective had been fitted for a pacemaker . . . or maybe he did.

Anyway, the cop spasmed and died, Tiffany’s mouth moved as she pounded the Plexiglas, and the Joker bowed. He was wearing an old-style tuxedo, the formal effect spoiled only slightly by a bright green cravat he wore in lieu of a bow tie, purple spats, and purple gloves. He completed his bow and looked at Tiffany in her box as if he had just noticed her. “God, how sad!” He pouted almost effeminately. “Poor girl . . . trying so hard, and your only reward is flop sweat?”

The Joker snapped his fingers. Water began pouring from invisible ducts in the box, pooling around Tiffany’s ankles. She screamed more loudly; it was just audible through the plastic. Fast Eddie Teck charged onstage, a switchblade knife in his hand. The Joker tasered him unconscious with a flick of his cane.

“For those of you who don’t know theater talk,” lisped the Joker, showing us flashes of his yellow teeth all the way back to the molars, “flop sweat is the ultimate pan notice . . . the sheen of ultimate failure, the glow of abject panic . . . the perspiration of expiration!”

The liquid rose to Tiffany’s shoulders, then to her chins. Her orange silk caftan floated around her. She jumped, pounded at the walls, clawed at plastic. The fluid rose until only her mouth and nose were clear of it as she strained against the roof of the box.

I rushed toward the stage and stopped as the Joker tasered two would-be rescuers in front of me. He snapped his fingers and a second cane appeared in his other hand.

“Tut, tut.” The Joker grinned. “Never interrupt an artist at work.” He glanced over his shoulder at Tiffany. The box had filled with clear liquid; she was no longer struggling. A few final bubbles of air rose from her nose and open mouth and tangled in her swaying hair.

The Joker walked over to the box and patted the side of it almost affectionately. “You don’t sweat much,” he said to Tiffany’s corpse. “For a fat lady.”

A dozen of us had come out of the shock and horror sufficiently to prepare to rush the Joker en masse. He twirled his cane. “Oh, I wouldn’t recommend giving fatso mouth-to-mouth,” he said, showing an expression of revulsion. “You see, this flop sweat isn’t water, it’s hydrochloric acid!” He grinned at us, waggled gloved fingers, and said, “Ta ta! See you all—or at least the survivors—at the joke-off!”

He laughed insanely. A bunch of us climbed onstage, rushed him. The Joker calmly bowed, caught one of the wires above the box, and rose out of sight into the darkness.

It took us almost five minutes to find a fire ax to crack the plastic box.

It was acid.

The guy named Bruce appeared and performed the next night at the Carob Club. He was awful. He did a routine that wouldn’t have gotten a laugh in 1952, much less during the beginning of the hip, raunchy nineties. The jokes were flat, his timing was nonexistent, he didn’t seem to care whether the audience was there or not, and his body language was bad. I mean, I saw the guy move before and after the show, and although he dressed like a cartoon of a pimp—zoot-suit-shouldered polyester gold jacket, baggy green pants, a matching monkey-puke-green open-collar shirt with layers of gold chains showing, even a greasy little Wayne Newton moustache that looked like an anemic caterpillar had crawled onto his upper lip to die—despite all that, this guy moved like an athlete. No, better than that, he was as unselfconsciously graceful as a big cat on the veldt.

But on stage . . . klutzville. He moved like Pee Wee Herman doing an imitation of Richard Nixon.

The audience didn’t boo him, they just sat and stared as if a traffic accident was occurring on stage. There was even a splattering of applause when he got off—probably from pure relief. I mean, the man was bad.

That’s why it was all the more confusing that night when I was hiking the six blocks to catch the subway up to Gotham Center where I’d catch the el out to Finger Park station, and who do I see down an alley but Bruce. I mean, I wouldn’t have been surprised to see this guy heading down an alley in search of a flophouse . . . he wore one weird suit and had that handsome but driven look, sort of like some out-of-work actors I’ve known . . . but there he is, 2:00 a.m. in an alley, in the rain, and he’s getting into a limousine. The chauffeur is some old guy, and it’s some stretched European ubermenschen limousine! It’s hard for most of us to take the tension and abuse and we’re all hoping for a break, the big time, money we can’t make any other way . . . or at least any other legal way. So why the hell would this poor schmuck take all the abuse and embarrassment if he didn’t have to? A guy who could afford a European limousine like that could buy an audience.

The next night at the Pit Stop, a strip joint that does comedy every Wednesday, Bruce was there again. Same routine. Same floppo, although this crowd was boozed up enough to start booing early. They were on the verge of throwing things when Bruce wrapped it up, bowed into that wall of boos, and walked calmly offstage.

Fast Eddie was ready to go on after him. Eddie leaned over to me and whispered, “Anybody’d look good after this jerk.”

Later, Boonie Sandhill and I went up to this Bruce guy in the green room.

“Howdy, y’all,” said Boonie, showing off the prognathous underbite that passed for a grin with him. “Caught your monologue, man. It’s . . . uh . . . original. Real different. Makes the rest of us look the same as stripes on a coon’s tail.”

Bruce raised an eyebrow and nodded, obviously not sure if Boonie was pulling his chain or not. I wasn’t either. We made introductions, shook hands. The guy’s handshake was easygoing enough, but I had the idea he could crush my fingers like breadsticks if he wanted to.

“Bruce,” said Boonie. “Is that your first name or last?”

The guy twitched a smile. “It’s my stage name. My . . . stand-up-comic pseudonym.”

Boonie rolled his eyes at the vocabulary. I said, “Any reason you chose the name Bruce?”

Bruce hesitated. “Homage to Lenny Bruce, I guess. He was sort of my hero.”

Boonie and I glanced at each other. This guy’s style and content bore about as much resemblance to Lenny Bruce’s stuff as did Mr. Rogers.

“Hero, huh?” said Boonie. “Too bad Lenny O.D.’d on speed.”

“Yes,” said Bruce. He was watching the closed-circuit monitor the Pit Stop had to let the green-room folks watch the action on stage. It was a crude picture—stationary camera, black-and-white fuzzy picture with poor sound—but Bruce seemed rapt. “It is too bad,” he said. “Lenny Bruce would have had a great future.”

Boonie and I looked at each other again. This guy was as miserable a liar as he was a comic; anybody who knew anything about Lenny Bruce knew that he died of an overdose of heroin.

“How come you joined the cavalcade of stars?” asked Boonie.

Bruce rubbed his chin. The guy was older than I was, but I have no idea how much older. He had the sort of rugged but understated good looks that lets a man ignore birthdays between his early thirties and late fifties. “I wanted a crack at the Gotham City Laughs of Tomorrow competition,” he said.

“You mean the big jerk-off?” said Boonie.

“Joke-off,” I said. “We call it the joke-off.”

Bruce nodded, eyes roving back to the closed-circuit TV. I had the idea that nothing made this man laugh; the idea of him making others laugh seemed . . . well . . . laughable.

“Don’t you worry about getting killed?” asked Boonie. There was no banter in his voice now and very little southern accent.

Bruce raised an eyebrow. “Oh, you mean that Joker fellow . . .”

“Yeah, that Joker fellow,” mimicked Boonie. “He sorta caught some of our attention.”

Bruce nodded as if mulling this over. “Sure, it worries me. But I figure it’s a chance I have to take to get a shot at the bigtime for the Gotham Comedy . . . ah . . . the joke-off. The odds seem decent.”

Boonie started to make some smart-ass reply, but I surprised him and myself by elbowing him to shut up and saying, “Right, man. That’s the way most of us feel. Say, Boonie and I are going out for coffee after the last show. Want to come?”

Bruce seemed to weigh the invitation with the same seriousness as he did everything else. “Yes,” he said. “I would.”

For the next week or so, Boonie and I spent a lot of time with Bruce after the show—in those thin, cold hours between the closing of the nightclubs and the rising of the sun through Gotham’s smog banks. Usually we hit an all-night cafe, mainlined strong coffee, and talked about comedy. Boonie and I talked about comedy. Bruce listened a lot. To tell the truth, he was a nice-enough guy. Just way too serious to be funny. He was even serious about comedy. Actually, he seemed to want to talk about the Joker most of the time: What did we think made the Joker do what he did? Why would the Joker be killing stand-up comics? What did we think of the Joker’s sense of humor?

“That ain’t a sense of humor, man,” Boonie answered more than once. “This Joker pissant is nuts. His idea of a punchline is pain.” And then Boonie would say, “Y’all want to analyze everything, Bruce. Petey and me, we just want to get laughs.”

“But just what, precisely, makes people laugh?” Bruce asked late one night, early one morning. Outside the diner, cold rain was turning to snow in front of the street-sweeping machines.

Boonie snorted. “Shit-fire, boy. If we knew that, old Pete and me’d be livin’ in Bel Aire an’ sittin’ on Johnny Carson’s couch twice a week.”

“But there must be some formula,” persisted Bruce. “Some secret.”

Boonie shook his head. “If there is, nobody knows it. Good comedy’s like . . . like good sex . . .”

“Good sex?” repeated Bruce. Any other comic would have snapped back, “Is there such a thing as bad sex, lint brain?” but Bruce was listening again. Seriously. “Uh-uh,” I interrupted. “Not sex. Surfing.”

Both of them looked at me.

“I mean it,” I said. I’d had a good night. The laughs had been strong and constant and sincere. “When I was out in California last summer, watching them surf at Malibu, I realized that a good stand-up routine’s like that. You gotta catch the wave just right . . . it’s like judging the audience . . . then get a good start, stay right on the break or curl or pipeline or whatever they call that sweet point just under the crest . . . and then ride it for all its worth, but still know when to end it.” I stopped, embarrassed, and slurped cold coffee.

Boonie stared at me. Bruce said, “And what’s the secret of riding the wave?”

For once my gaze was just as serious as Bruce’s. “The secret is using material that means something,” I said, surprised to hear me talking this way. “To go at the thing that’s most serious to you, most . . . well, most sacred . . . and to make it funny.”

Bruce pondered his own coffee cup.

I pushed ahead. “I mean, look at your material, man. It’s stuff you bought from a street-comer gag writer. Am I right?”

He nodded. I think he nodded.

“It’s not you, man,” I said. “It has nothing to do with you. It’s not what scares you, what hurts you, what bugs you . . . you got to go for the stuff that’s hiding in the deepest closets, then get it out. Share it with others who’re hiding the same thing. Make it funny. Take some of the sting out of it.”

I had Bruce’s attention. “Do you do that, Pete?”

“Yeah,” I said and sipped coffee. I was lying. I never dealt with the core of me—the guilt and fear and pride and terror I’d felt since I was four years old and realized that I was black: middle-class, reasonably well-educated, not street smart, not cool, but black. I realized why and who I’d really been lecturing there: I’d never had the guts to do a routine about my childhood in Charity Hills, or what it means to be the only kid on your block who didn’t belong to a gang. “Yeah,” I lied again, looking at my watch. “Hell, it’s almost four-thirty. I don’t have to be at Burger Biggie until ten, but it’s a little late.” I threw some change on the table. “See you losers tomorrow.”

Boonie gave me his hillbilly grin. “Yeah, y’all can see me hang out my dirty linen then. I ain’t got no hangups about talkin’ about my miserable upbringin’ and poor but honest family.”

“Yeah,” I said, pausing at the door. “Tell us again about how you slept on bare mattresses with burlap for a cover . . . too poor to buy sheets or blankets.”

Boonie grinned more broadly. “Shee-it. We had sheets. But they was cut full a holes ’cause of all the Klan meetin’s we had to go to.”

I shook my head. “See you tomorrow, Bruce. I’ll watch you bomb, my cracker friend.”

Instead, I watched Boonie die.

We were uptown, at the ritzy Chez Harpo, and the place was crawling with cops. We were only a day away from the selection deadline for the joke-off, and there must have been forty comics competing for mike time that night. Bruce didn’t survive the auditions for Chez, but he was there that night. So were about fifty cops: on the roof, backstage, in the audience, in uniform out front, and monitoring things from a trailer command center out back.

The mayor and the commissioner of police . . . what’s-his-name . . . Gordon, had decided that the Joker comedy killings were making Gotham look bad. Whatever the reason for the security, I didn’t see any way the Joker could get through it.

He did.

Boonie had them laughing. He was riding the wave real well, letting the laughter build and then punching it up higher, pausing at just the right spots, using the silences, when suddenly one of the silences stretched too far. The audience paused to breathe, waiting for the next funny bit.

Boonie started smiling as if he had just thought of something funnier than the story he’d planned to tell. The audience tittered in anticipation. Boonie’s smile grew wider. His lips stretched back over his rear teeth. Some of the audience’s laughter fell away, turned to gasps.

Boonie’s color drained until his sunburned Georgia look gave way to a deathly pallor, grew paler still—by the time people started screaming, Boonie’s complexion was the kind of white a corpse might show after a week in the water. His lips were stretched from ear to ear as if someone had pulled his cheeks back with meat hooks.

Boonie dropped the mike, gurgled something, and collapsed.

The cops went nuts. Bruce was the first one to Boonie, but I was there a second later. My friend was dead, already cooling to the touch.

Bruce pounded his fist on his knee. “Damn, damn, damn . . .”

“What?” I said. “How?”

Bruce touched Boonie’s neck where the tiniest dart was visible, barely larger than a mosquito. “Joker Venom. He’s used it for years. Keeps altering the formula so no antidote works. Hardly elegant, but very effective. A message.”

The cops were sealing all exits, searching the premises, frisking patrons, shouting orders.

Bruce shook his head. ‘The Joker’s gone by now. Probably disguised as a police officer.”

I was crying. I couldn’t help it. “But why Boonie? Why him?” I spread my jacket over my friend’s face to hide the terrible rictus. “I mean, he wasn’t the best comic tonight. Certainly not the worst. Why’d that bastard choose him?”

Bruce seemed elsewhere—not in shock like the rest of us, merely—elsewhere. “I thought the Joker might be eliminating competitors,” he said, almost speaking to himself, “but now I know it’s something else.”

I wiped away tears with the back of my hand. “What, dammit? Is he trying to sabotage the joke-off?”

“No. Definitely not.”

Paramedics and cops had shoved through and pushed Bruce and me away from Boonie. They worked fast, tossing IVs, syringe cases, and technical terms around . . . but Boonie stayed dead.

I stood up and looked out over the heads of the crowd. “It doesn’t matter,” I said. “I’m going to enter that damn contest and win. Win for Boonie and for me. No way that this homicidal asshole is going to scare us away.”

“You’re right,” said Bruce. “We do have to be in it. Both of us. And we will.”

The word came just like a summons from the Almighty. Uncle Louis would have loved it. He always wanted me to be someone genuinely significant—like an African Methodist preacher-man. Becoming a fast-track management clone at Burger Biggie was sort of okay—but a no-account stand-up comic didn’t cut it.

Anyhow, the message from God arrived via Gotham Bonded Messenger. No bicycle delivery here—nosirree. I was just heading out of my apartment to cover the night shift for an asshole buddy whose plane had gotten stranded in Cleveland when he’d gone home to see his father. Dad had started that long day’s journey into kidney cancer . . . Anyhow, I saw the sparkling silver BMW pull up to the curb. I figured it had to be a crack dealer, so I ignored it.

Naturally I was surprised when a hunched-over guy in a blue uniform got out and said directly to me, “You would be Mr. Tulley?”

I resisted the impulse to say something like, “Why yes, Mr. Stanley?” and just nodded my head.

The old guy crabbed up to me and handed over an envelope. Then he produced a smoky-gray Lucite clipboard and said, “Sign here.” No “please.”

What the heck. I signed. Could be there was an inheritance, though far as I knew, nobody in the family had died. Maybe it was a desperate creditor. I checked the return address. Just a box number in Clovertide, up on the north side.

I shrugged and ran my right index fingernail under the flap. The folded letter felt like vellum. I straightened it, smoothed the creases, and read the calligraphy. Classy stuff. At first I didn’t register what it was I was seeing on that page. Then I let out a whoop that probably triggered all the car alarms on the block and raised at least a half-dozen of my more gris-gris-conscious dead kinfolk.

I was in. Damn. How about that. But I was supposed to report to some address up on the north side for an orientation. Tonight.

Faulkner said that when it came to sacrifice for writers, a good novel was worth any number of little old ladies. I figured I could extend that to artists of all kinds, so I kept it in mind when I called my understaffed B.B. and told the woman who answered that I was going to be a no-show tonight.

“What’s wrong?” she said. “You sick?”

“Nope,” I said. “I just got a formal notice saying I’m going to be competing in the big joke-off, the Gotham City Laughs of Tomorrow contest, the golden path to the Johnny Carson Show. There’s a heavy-duty meeting tonight.”

“Right,” she said, clearly sounding as if she didn’t believe the tone of my voice, much less a word I was saying. “Get in when you can, Pete. We really need you. Listen, take something, get better fast.” She clicked off the line.

Yeah, right. I’d better get better fast. The joke-off was only three days away. And me, I was going to be there. Son of a bitch. I started humming along with the time on the oldies station I’d left on as a burglar deterrent: “Laugh, laugh, I thought I’d die . . .”

I took the train north and got off at a station just a little different than my usual stop. This one had spotless tile—and no graffiti—with tasteful turquoise accent stripes. Maybe the stations downtown did, too, but you would never notice for the krylon street art. When I got on the T-local at the Sprang Street station, I’d seen a jagged scream painted on the wall in Day-Glo purple: JOKER LIVES. Someone else had sprayed an X over the second word and added LAUGHS in bright scarlet.

The address on the invite was two blocks west. This was a business neighborhood, lots of low office blocks in brick and glass. It was getting dark now. I hardly saw anybody who looked like me—hell, there was hardly anybody at all on the street. They’d probably all headed home at five to the ’burbs.

My destination was a nondescript office tower that disappeared somewhere up there in the darkness. There weren’t any lit windows. When I walked past the alley that bordered one side, I caught a glimpse of a familiar vehicle—A European stretch limo parked in the back.

Bruce was here, too? I realized I was phrasing it in my head as a question. I hadn’t seen him perform since Boonie bought the farm, but I couldn’t imagine his improving sufficiently to make any kind of final cut for anything. I mean, he was a nice guy and he had heart, but Jesus what a stiff.

“I think I owe this to you, Pete.” The deep baritone came from the darkness behind my left shoulder. I jumped. A reassuring hand came down, the steel fingers wrapping around my scapula. I wasn’t reassured. “You taught me some first-rate lessons.”

“Holy shit!” I said. I knew who was there. “You scared the crap out of me.”

“I don’t recall you being so scatological in your delivery,” said Bruce. I could hear the trace of a smile in his voice. I turned and looked at him. He was dressed somberly in dark wool trousers and a black turtleneck. More like his namesake, it suddenly occurred to me. Good for him. Anything beat that Bozo zoot-suit he’d boasted the first time I’d seen him bomb. “Congratulations on jumping the final hurdle to the joke-off.”

“You, too,” I said. He put out his hand and I took it. Again, I felt like I was sticking my fingers in a walnut crusher. “Do you know what we’re getting tonight?” Bruce shook his head and motioned toward the dark building with the folded letter in his left hand. “I know only as much as you do.”

Both of us started walking toward the front door. I realized there was a light inside, the dim glow from a gang of security monitors behind a lobby desk. The glass door opened as we approached. There were two big guys in rent-a-cop uniforms waiting for us. Both had mean eyes, though they each smiled. “Mr. Tulley? Mr., ah, Bruce?” said the bigger of the pair. At our nods, the other guy checked his clipboard and made marks. Obviously they’d been well-briefed. “Please take the elevator on the left and go up to the thirtieth floor. You both want room one-oh-one.”

Bruce cocked his head. “Why is room one-oh-one on the thirtieth floor?”

The first guard shrugged. “I didn’t set up the numbering system. I just know which place you’re supposed to go.”

“I was just wondering.”

“You two are the last,” said the second guard. “You better hurry. Mr. Carson’s waiting.”

We got in the elevator and punched thirty. As the doors slid shut, I said to Bruce, “Something significant about room one-oh-one?”

“Aside from the fact one wouldn’t expect it to be on the thirtieth floor, it’s also the designation of the room in 1984 where prisoners encounter the thing they fear most.”

“Swell,” I said. The elevator car suddenly seemed smaller, more claustrophobic.

Actually, room 101 turned out to be a respectably sized suite that didn’t seem sinister at all. Nearly a dozen and a half comics were there, all ones I knew and a few I was friends with. Then there was Johnny. It was kind of weird seeing him without Ed or Doc. He was surrounded with four or five harried-looking aides. He was taller than I expected, but what can you expect when you’ve only seen someone on a nineteen-inch tube? I guess maybe I was expecting him to be nattily dressed in an Armani. Nope. He was wearing a perfectly tailored suit that I was pretty sure was from his own line. I couldn’t be positive because I wasn’t in that shopping bracket, but I figured Johnny wouldn’t be disloyal to his own label.

One of his assistants raised his voice and said, “If you’ll all find a seat, Mr. Carson would like to have a few words with you.”

I sat on a leather-upholstered couch with Bruce on one side of me, Diana Mulhollen on the other. She’s such a sweet kid. I was glad she’d made the final cut. As long as I still won.

Johnny got up in front of us and said, “Ladies and Gentlemen, I’ll keep this short. You’re all here because you’ve been selected from among all of Gotham City’s considerable ranks of the comically gifted.” He grinned. “You’re all among that select group of folks who end up going to parties that have been primed by some friend who told everybody else there, ‘Hey, you’ve got to talk to so-and-so, he’s the funniest guy you’ll ever meet.’ So what happens? You get there and everyone’s looking at you expectantly, waiting for you to knock ’em dead.” We smiled. Some of us snickered. Johnny smiled back and continued, “It’s a tough life, being funny. It’s our hope that the Gotham City Laughs of Tomorrow competition will make that life easier for some of you.”

He went on to talk about the charities that would benefit, and about the live national TV hookup that would carry the proceedings across all America. Then he got to what I suspected most of us really wanted to hear about.

“The winner will be on the show the following week. We’ll fly you out to Burbank and put you up like a king—or queen. And if that works out . . .” Johnny grinned and spread his hands beneficently. ‘There’s no telling where you’ll go. This will be the break of a lifetime.”

I sensed eighteen indrawn breaths being held. Well, maybe seventeen, including mine. I’d glanced aside at Bruce. He didn’t seem quite as mesmerized as the rest of us.

“My associates,” said Johnny, “will give you full details about your time leading up to the competition. There will be,” he added, “no formal rehearsals as such.

The director will want to block out times with you, but you won’t deliver your material.” Diane and I exchanged glances. “The idea is to keep your humor as fresh as you can, as topical as you wish. Besides, most of you are already familiar with your fellow comics’ routines.” Someone laughed appreciatively. There were smiles. The rest was pretty much pro forma, with the exception of a revelation that stirred some enthusiasm. Robin Williams would make a special appearance at the beginning of the show. Very brief, but very funny, Johnny said. That was great. I couldn’t think of anyone living I would rather have as a comedy role model.

Johnny asked for questions. There weren’t many. Then he excused himself and turned us over to his aides, who passed out laminated photo passes and rehearsal schedules. It turned out the telecast was originating from the Aladdin Theater, the very same place where Tiffany was drowned in flop sweat.

That didn’t make anybody happy. Fast Eddie Teck brought it up. Johnny suggested we all just consider the competition a dedicatory memorial to Tiffany, George Marlin, Boonie, and the others in our little community who had died as the butts of the Joker’s sadistic jokes.

Then the meeting was over. With a smile—I realized that Johnny had never displayed a straight face for the entirety of the evening—our host thanked us for our time and wished us well on Saturday night. People started to shuffle, shrugging on jackets and coats.

“Come on, Pete,” said Bruce. “I need to be down at street level before the crowd.”

I had no reason to stick around, so I beat him to the elevator and punched the button. There was something about Johnny’s smile that weirded me out.

“One to a customer, gents and gentlettes,” I said, “get ’em while they’re cold.” Within five minutes I’d found myself in a situation that reminded me of doing volunteer labor (or not-so-volunteer if a guy were directed by the court to do a community service gig) in a downtown mission bread line.

When Bruce and I had exited the office building and walked to the head of the alley where his car had been parked, I found that the old codger who drove for him had turned that great gleaming barge around and popped the trunk lid. The luggage compartment was full of wrapped packages.

I looked down at them. “Bond market down, Bruce? You selling tailgate bargains now? Watches and Walkmen that fell off a truck, maybe?”

“I’m afraid not,” said Bruce. “But I would appreciate it if you would walk over by the door and steer everyone here to me. Everyone.” The tone in his voice was all business. I wasn’t about to say no.

Getting sixteen comics to congregate in the dark by an alley mouth where one of their colleagues was handing out butcher-paper-wrapped parcels was not the easiest job I’ve ever done.

“Listen,” I said to them. “Humor him. Maybe he’s the Joker. Just take a package.”

“What is this shit, man?” said Fast Eddie, bouncing his packet on his palm a couple times. He tugged at the twine wrapping it, ripped some of the paper loose. “Old clothes?”

He was the last one to accept a package.

“All right,” said Bruce. “Please, just a minute of your time. Then you can go.”

They quieted. They crowded around the rear of the limo. They were still pumped up with the afterglow of having rubbed shoulders with the guy who could make the rest of their lives work like Swiss clockwork.

Bruce looked seriously at us all. “This might well save all our lives.” His tone was convincing as all hell. “And if you think it’s too weird, please, just trust me. It might save you from ending up like poor Tiffany or the rest.”

Any grumbling or snickers ended at that.

“And if it is not something that’s needed,” Bruce continued, “then perhaps we still can provide a finale for the joke-off that no one in the audience will ever forget.” That was the hook. Having sunk it, Bruce went on. What he suggested to us was a hell of a lot funnier than any of his onstage jokes had been.

I like to think I own a healthy amount of self-confidence, but let me tell you—for three days I woke up soaked in, wore under my sodden clothes, and tried to wash off at night, more anticipatory flop sweat than had devoured poor Tiffany’s whole body. I must have lost twenty percent of my bodyweight from evaporation, and didn’t even have any spare pounds to lose.

I kept thinking about what I was going to spring on Johnny and Robin and sixty million viewers Saturday night. None of my usual material seemed funny anymore. Maybe it was time for fast-food jokes. Probably not.

Damn.

Maybe I could find a way to use the package Bruce had handed me out of the cavernous trunk of his limo as a prop. Maybe not. I wondered whether I was going to get ulcers out of this. Herpes lesions. Colitis. Pellagra. Pellagra?

I kept on sweating.

Saturday came and with it, the sort of feeling I hadn’t had since I was five years old. I can remember wondering whether my folks would remember my fifth birthday. I wondered whether my dad would come back from a business trip down south. His trips on the road had been getting longer and longer. The feeling was anticipatory and scary, and a little sick with apprehension. When Dad showed and the cake started to smoke in the kitchen and the party started, it was almost an anticlimax.

I woke up at six, then dozed and rocked and tossed until about noon, when I finally rolled out of bed. My dad called ten minutes later to wish me luck and to inform me that the whole family would be home watching the show on TV. I’d gotten eight comp tickets for good seats at the Aladdin, but there were just too many in the family who wanted to go. So no one was. Dad had given the tickets to our church pastor and he was going to find worthy recipients. Shoot. I didn’t say anything, but I was willing to bet I could have scalped those suckers for enough to keep me at least a month if I didn’t win the joke-off.

Then Mom came on, and then Cousin Sook, and everybody else who was over at the house, and they all said they loved me and hoped I’d do ’em proud. I promised I would.

Then I went into the bathroom and threw up.

The Aladdin seemed a lot different than it had the evening of the fatal Tuesday Night Laugh Riot. The few handfuls of human beings, both performers and audience, who had been in attendance then had been dwarfed by this old Arabian nights deco barn. Tonight the two thousand seats were full. It was obvious that there had been a quick sprucing up. The sheets of paint, which had threatened to peel all the way off the ceiling and skate down into the crowd, had all been scraped and replaced. The gigantic stage curtains had been dusted—the maintenance crew must have beat them with telephone poles. But the place still smelled of mildew and outright rot.

The plan was simple. All us contestants were to be seated right at the front in the orchestra section. No hiding back in the green room. We would be in plain sight so the cameras could zoom in and catch our sick expressions as other performers outclassed us. Johnny was slated for the opening monologue; then he’d introduce Robin Williams, and Robin would hand the show back to Johnny. Then it would be our turn. Five minutes max. Not even the fifteen Warhol had promised us all.

I amused myself for a while looking back for friendly faces in the rapidly filling auditorium. I didn’t see any, at least no one who was familiar.

“Hello, Pete,” I stopped craning my neck. Bruce settled himself in the theater seat beside mine. No mutant zoot tonight. He wore a perfectly cut tux. Very formal-looking. Class act. I started to rethink my policy of wearing exactly the sort of bright street clothes I had worn to the comedy clubs. At least my shirt was clean. I’d remembered to select one off a hanger in the clean end of the closet just as I was ready to go out and treat myself to a cab over to the theater.

“Hey, Bruce.” I wished I felt as light as my voice. “How’s it going?”

“I’m hoping for the best—and wishing you well.” Those dark eyes stabbed toward mine. “You remembered to bring the package?”

I nodded. Yeah, I’d remembered after almost spacing it out. I’d been out the door with the key in the deadbolt before I remembered the parcel. Almost didn’t go back. Then said the hell with it and unlocked the door again.

“Actually,” said Bruce, surveying out colleagues, our friends, our competition, “I wish us all a great amount of good fortune tonight.”

There was an undertone I couldn’t quite interpret. “What’s that supposed to mean?”

He smiled slightly—“Nothing important.”—and hesitated even more slightly, but I still caught it. “Perhaps I’m a bit concerned about flop-sweat.”

I laughed. “Don’t worry. I’ve cornered the market right here in my armpits.”

He touched my wrist reassuringly and sat back in his seat. The floor director signaled that it was one minute until airtime. The lights were already uncomfortably warm. Then the manic theme music—sort of a strange mixture of “March of the Marionettes” and the main theme from Bubo the Clown’s Afterschool Fun Club—swelled up from the house PA system, and we were off.

God, the Gotham City Laughs of the Future competition started. The joke-off was on the air. I was simultaneously terrified and ecstatic.

And then, thirty seconds later, I was only terrified.

It happened almost as soon as the offstage announcer introduced Johnny and he virtually skipped onto the stage. The follow-spot found him and he waited patiently for the wild applause to die down.

“Good evening, ladies and germs,” he said, grinning with all those sparkling teeth. “Or maybe just good evening, germs.”

At that, I don’t know what we all expected. Asian flu jokes, maybe.

That’s not what we got. From the contestants’ section, I had an especially good view of what happened next. Johnny cupped his hands into claws and reached up toward his own face. He sank his nails into his rosy cheeks and started moving his fingers as though kneading dough.

Then he ripped off his own face. He pulled away what seemed to be strips of pink flesh as the audience stared. As my little sister would say, it was totally gross. Another set of features emerged. I admit it—I was expecting Freddy Kruger.

It wasn’t. It was Robin Williams.

Ripples of applause started with us in the front, then spread back into the loge and the balconies. On the stage, Robin Williams grinned and it seemed like he was looking straight down at me. He held up his palms, acknowledging the delighted cheers.

I hadn’t realized he was so tall.

Then Robin Williams ripped off his face, too. Just like Johnny. What the hell was this going to be, an endless series of Chinese boxes in the form of latex full-face masks?

I stared at the new persona of the man on stage. He yanked off his toupee and fluffed out his scraggly hair. Green hair.

Oh shit, I thought, along with, I’m sure, most of the rest of the audience all at the same time. It’s the Joker.

The guy on the stage grinned from ear to ear, but he didn’t look like a happy camper. “Ladies and gentlemen,” he said, “a funny thing happened on the way to the theater.” There was a great deal of consternation behind me in the audience. The Joker held up his hands for silence. There was a rapid-fire crackle of automatic weapons’ fire and a few screams. The audience quieted down.

“That’s better,” said our lanky host. He slipped off his tux jacket and slipped the sleeves inside out. When he donned the garment again, I saw it was a tasteful metallic purple. This guy was for real, I thought. This wasn’t another gag. I suddenly flashed on George Marlin and Tiffany and Boonie, all their faces, twisted and pained and dying.

I’ll cop to panicking. I started to bolt out of my seat, but I felt a hand firm as wrought iron holding me down. “Hang in there,” said Bruce. “You’ll never get past his men.”

That brought me back. I looked around. All the rent-a-cop security types were clustered around the auditorium doors. Funny, I’d never seen rent-a-cops carrying assault scatterguns and automatic weapons before.

The Joker cleared his throat with a sound like scraping snot off sandpaper with a putty knife. “As I was saying, a funny thing occurred. I happened by a nearby warehouse where your favorites, Mr. Carson and Mr. Williams, are presently safe but confined.” He paused. “They said to say they were sorry they couldn’t make it here in person tonight, but that they were tied up.” The Joker laughed. He was the only one.

He stalked across the stage to the right, then back to the left. The spot followed. I noticed that the lighting tech had slipped in a purple gel. I had a feeling the Joker had covered every detail.

“If you’re thinking that the outside world will see all this on television and collectively alert the National Guard and the Marines, be advised I’ve addressed that possibility. Even as I speak, some sixty million of your fellows are watching an advisory crawl across their screens apologizing for technical difficulties. By way of substitution, a rerun of Wild Kingdom is playing.” The Joker giggled.

“Now.” The Joker stopped centerstage and leered down at us in the first few rows. “Let us cut right to the heart of the matter, figuratively now, later perhaps literally. I have reason to believe that among you is my old nemesis, the Batman.” I could hear murmurs in the audience. “Do I speak plainly enough?”

I think the question was rhetorical. I leaned closer to Bruce. “The comics he killed . . .”

“Bait.” Bruce’s voice was quiet. I looked sidewise at him. He stared at the Joker like a tomcat stares at another tom who’s invaded his territory. That fixedness frightened me.

“Don’t worry,” said the Joker. “You’ll still get to see the show you bought expensive tickets for, but you’ll get a real bonus in addition. The comics who competed for the Laughs of Tomorrow finals are hoping for a new life. Now they can expect an additional treat—the possibility of death as well.”

“He’s gonna kill us all?” I said.

Bruce answered, “I don’t think so. His plan will be mad, but it will still be a plan.”

“Anyone who pays close attention to that caped clod who hounds me,” said the Joker, “knows he possesses all the granite-jawed wit of Mount Rushmore. We are about to discover just how minuscule a sense of humor the man owns.” He gestured toward us in the orchestra. “All of you up here. All eighteen. Now!”

I guess none of us saw any room for argument. Not with the Joker. Not with the two guys with Uzis who escorted us onto the stage.

When we were assembled like a herd—a gaggle—a flock—I don’t know what they say out in the sticks—of sheep guarded by gun-toting goons, the Joker surveyed us cheerily. “You’re all going to do your routines,” he said. “I’m the judge for this. But guess what? I’m not looking for the funniest one anymore. I am searching for the worst, dumbest, least-funny among you. That one, I’m guessing, will be the Batman.” He chortled. “Then we’ll see just how a bad comedian dies on stage.”

We all looked at each other. At least Diana Mulhollen and a woman named Winnie Morales had nothing to worry about. The thought must have occurred simultaneously to Winnie. She held up her hand like a schoolgirl.

“A question?” said the Joker, “or do you have to go to the little girls’ room?”

“Do I gotta go through my routine, too?” said Winnie. “Everyone does,” came the answer. “My dark foe is a

devilishly clever master of disguise, even as I am. Each one of you is suspect.”

“But—” said Winnie. I halfway expected her to drop her trousers and give the Joker some physiological proof of her not being Batman.

“No exceptions, unless you’d like to forfeit your participation in the competition . . .” The Joker’s tone was ominous. Winnie seemed to pick that up. She said nothing and lowered her gaze to the stage at her feet.

“All right, then,” said the Joker, his tone lightening. “Let’s get to it. Time for our first contestant. Remember, friends, you get points for delivery and timing. For being funny, you get your life.”

This was absolutely crazy, I thought. Batman working incognito as an aspiring stand-up comic? Bat guano. I remembered the man I’d met in the police interrogation after George Marlin’s death. That aura of brooding power wasn’t anywhere among my colleagues.

I glanced over at Bruce as we both got up from our seats. That poor sucker might as well have a signed death warrant. He was as funny as—I tried to stop the thought. Too late.—a grave.

“Don’t worry, Pete,” he said. “Well all do our best. We’ll all pull through this together.”

Sure, I thought. Together—in a mass grave. One big pine box. Piano crate. God, was I getting hysterical? I took a deep breath. I figured I’d better start thinking about how to buff up my material to a higher sheen.

But as the Joker consulted his list, picking the first contestant, in my head I kept seeing a field of bleached skulls. Eighteen of them.

“. . . so the chief says, ‘Fine, then. I decree death by mongo . . .’ ” And that wrapped up five minutes of pretty decent material by Goombah Dozois, the Cajun comic. The audience exploded into deafening applause. Goombah wasn’t that good, but I’d gotten the feeling as we’d gone down the list of contestants that the crowd both needed a catharsis and wanted to do whatever they could to help us all survive. So they cheered everyone, good, bad, or indifferent. And even under the circumstances of being forced to be funny at gunpoint, or maybe because of it, some of us weren’t even as hilarious as we would have been at, say, the Carob Club Comedy Countdown.

Goombah staggered out of the spotlight and rejoined us. The Joker scanned the list and said, “All right, my friends, we only have a few contestants to go.” That included me. “So keep your pants on.” Everytime he used one of those damned catch-phrases, we all cringed, not knowing if he was about to tie it to some crude wordplay-made-flesh. This time, he didn’t.

“Our next competitor is . . . Mr. Bruce!” The crowd clapped. Bruce and I exchanged looks. His was enigmatic. He touched my arm with those iron fingers and then stepped into the spotlight. He blinked a couple times, I guess adjusting to the glare. He glanced at the Joker, then turned fully to the crowd.

“If any of you have heard me in the clubs, you know what kind of material I use. ‘Hey, being a filthy rich kid isn’t all it’s cracked up to be . . . I remember how other kids brought their lunch boxes to school. I had caterers from Maxim’s come to the cafeteria every day.’ Not too funny, right?”

Right, I thought. Not too funny. Not then and not now.

Bruce paused a moment. A long moment. “I’ve been thinking a lot,” he said, “about something my friend, Pete Tulley, told me.” He shrugged. “I started thinking about some things I’d vowed never to think of again.” I heard something in his voice. As little as I knew Bruce, I could still hear the keen of pain. “Let me tell you about someone I used to know.”

I sneaked a look at the Joker. He was frowning, angular chin propped on one startlingly white palm, fingers curled up around his mouth like spider legs.

“This was when I was a student in the fourth grade,” said Bruce. Huh? I thought. Richie Rich’s childhood anecdotes? “A new school-year had just started and I was in my homeroom class for the first time. It was right after lunch and I was logy. You know, feeling about like an anaconda that’s just eaten a goat. I could tell the teacher was, too.”

Good delivery, I thought. He’s picking up steam. The crowd could sense it. I saw some of the folks in the front starting to sit back in their seats instead of leaning forward anxiously.

“We looked like a perfectly good class, maybe thirty kids, all pink and scrubbed and full of enthusiasm. But as I said, we were all ready for an afternoon nap, and I think the new teacher was, too. Here he was, facing us all, and I think that for a moment, all he could do was to stare at us.” Bruce shook his head and smiled. “I think he decided to try something new. He figured he’d stall us for a bit, make conversation while he was picking which way he wanted to take the class.”

Hey, I tried to warn him telepathically, you’re starting to wander, just a little. Get back on track.

“Finally—it was only a few seconds, but it seemed like an hour in my mind—he started with the first student at the near end of the far left row, a boy. “Son,’ he said, ‘I’d like to find out a little bit about each of you. I want to ask about your families. Tell me something now, tell me what your father does.’

“So then the first boy said, ‘My dad’s a fire fighter.’ And he told him about what his father did. I guess that worked out so well, the teacher went on to the next student, a girl. ‘And what’s your father do?’ he asked. ‘He’s in the Army,’ came the answer. ‘He fights people.’ And so it went,” said Bruce. “On down the ranks of students, row by row, until he got to a young boy sitting right in back, in the very center.”

I was trying to think, did I know this joke? It was new to me. I wondered where Bruce had dug up some new material. Or maybe he was spinning the truth, maybe this really was something that had happened to him back—I still couldn’t quite believe it—when he was a fourth-grader.

“This little boy was short and dark—dark hair, dark eyes. He was quiet and very, very serious,” said Bruce. “You could tell just by looking at him that he was lonely.” There was the touch of something I couldn’t immediately identify in Bruce’s voice. Then it came to me—it was the sound of someone who wanted to cry, but couldn’t. Just that tiniest of cracks.

“I was that little boy.”

There was an odd tone in the way Bruce said it. I felt like I should hold my breath and stay very, very still.

“So then the teacher looked at the little boy and asked, ‘Son, what does your father do?’ I didn’t answer, but just stared back at him. I think he suddenly knew that he ought to drop it then and there, but he didn’t.”

Bruce coughed and offered the crowd an apologetic half-smile. “But then it was for him about like it is for me now. He just kept on going, bulled right on ahead. He tried to get through what he thought was my shyness and said, ‘It’s okay, son, you can talk to me. Tell me what your dad does.’

“I finally looked him straight in the eye and said in a low voice, ‘Sorry, sir, he doesn’t do anything. My father’s dead.’ ”

Somebody in the audience gasped. I swallowed. This was weird. There was something about Bruce’s delivery.

“He knew right then,” said Bruce, “that he ought to get out of this any way he could. He should go on to the next student. He was entering some kind of Vietnam of primary education.” He shook his head sadly. “He couldn’t. God knows why, but he looked back at the little dark-haired boy—me—and said, ‘It’s all right, son, go ahead and tell me . . . what did your daddy do before he died?”’

Bruce paused so momentarily that I thought I was maybe the only person catching him swallowing.

“I looked back at him, still straight in the eye, and said, ‘Well, he went cckcckccckkkccckkk!’ ” Bruce grabbed his own throat and mugged the visual image to go with the strangling sounds.

The crowd was stone silent.

It was like they didn’t know what to do, didn’t know how to react.

Then it began. A laugh somewhere in the balcony. A titter to stage-left in the loge. People giggled, groaned, started to guffaw. The laughter spread like the Philippine flu. So far as I could see, about the only people not absolutely breaking up were the thugs with machine guns.

Then the applause began to overwhelm the laughter. As best I could see Bruce’s features from the side, he looked overwhelmed, too. He bowed slightly.

Above the roar of the audience rose a cackling from the stage. I turned my head and saw the Joker on the floor. Literally. He was holding his sides and roaring with laughter, that terrible hyena bray I first heard at the Carob the night George Marlin blew his top.

I looked back at Bruce as he stared out over that ocean of reacting human beings. In his eyes I saw the shine of tears. What did this mean? I wondered. What had it cost?

The next one up was Winnie Morales. It was pretty obvious she didn’t relish having a turn in the barrel right after Bruce’s bravura performance. She stared out over the crowd, obviously swallowed, then said, “Okay, so there were these three clergy-guys walking down the street. There was a Jewish rabbi, a Baptist preacher-fella, and an Irish bishop. They were on their way to play golf, when suddenly Saint Peter . . .”

And the next one up was me.

Well, I figured I could beat Winnie Morales. Maybe.

I knew I couldn’t beat Bruce, but hey, I didn’t want to. I just wanted to save my own hide. At least that’s what I thought until I actually stood out there, bathed in a bloody red gel-light from the follow spots. I know it’s a cliché, but time slowed for me.

Bruce’s routine replayed in my head. Something came to me with all the subtlety of getting whupped up alongside the head with a flying mallet. I felt the shock of the brilliant white light, you know?

That tired old poor-little-rich-kid routine of Bruce’s had somehow evolved to what he’d performed tonight. I was pretty sure it hadn’t come easily. I still couldn’t quite see all the cross-connections—it really was hard to see Bruce as a little boy in the fourth grade. But somehow he knew something about parents and death and had formed it into an awful-yet-effective story that had destroyed an entire theater.

It came to me. Yeah, he’d learned from me, all right. He’d listened to what I’d said back when he and Boonie and I’d been talking. Then he did the things I’d never done. He’d faced up. He’d gone real.

Just like I claimed to do, but didn’t.

Hey, nothing like making myself feel like shit just when I was supposed to spend the most important five minutes of my life making people laugh.

The voice grated into my consciousness. “Oh, Mr. Tulley, are you going to perform or not? Has the cat got your tongue?”

Shit. I focused and saw the Joker smiling easily just a few yards away. Things snapped together inside. I hoped.

I nodded and took a deep breath. “Hey, how many of you out there realize I’m not really black?” That got a few titters. “Nope, truly I’m not. I’m black Irish.”

“Oh, yeah?” That was maybe the first heckler of the night. Good, I thought. Then I squinted and realized I’d been needled by one of the Joker’s goon squad.

So “Yeah,” I said. “The name on my driver’s license is O’Rio.” The thug looked bewildered. Nobody out beyond the lights laughed, so I used exaggerated cheerleading gestures to spell out the name I said. This time there was a ripple of laughter.

“Good, you got it. Am I going too fast for you? Hey, let’s go. You think it’s easy being an Oreo in the inner city, man? I mean, you should have heard me playing the dozens with tough dudes on the comer. I mean, they got to serve first—

“ ‘Hey, man, yo mama wears combat boots when she gives it away in the alley.’

“So I snap back with, ‘She ain’t givin’ it away, man. She’s in the alley pickin’ aluminum cans outta the Dumpster to pay for my Harvard education, man.’ ” More laughter. Thank God.

“No, I mean it—the other dudes from the block were like Fast Eddie Teck, you know? Carried switchblades. Me . . .” I slipped my hand into my hip pocket and pretended to snap something out. “One time this homeboy from the Night Vultures jumps me, and so I go for my calculator . . .”

A little more laughter. And so it goes.

When all of us were done, the Joker had the house lights brought up. The eighteen of us pretty much looked like the condemned, about to be shot as examples by some military junta in a soccer stadium.

“Well—” said the Joker. “That was quite a round of performances. I’m impressed that many of you, if you should survive this evening, might actually have a future in comedy—especially now that you’ll have a great new experience to draw upon. Think of me as your agent of change; but remember, if you use any material pertaining to yours truly, to give me due acknowledgment. Otherwise I’ll have to track you down and extract my fifteen percent.” He giggled. “And I’ll wager that, for most of you, fifteen percent is a great deal more than a mere pound of flesh.” He looked contemplative, as though imagining harvesting his fee.

Then his voice changed mercurially. “Ah, yes, the matter of the incognito Bat-comic. I rather unwisely predicted I would have to make final disposition of the least funny of you.” He ambled toward us. “Unfortunately that reflects badly on you.” The Joker raised his cane and lightly touched it to Winnie Morales’s chest. “Don’t worry, my dear, you seem too much the mammal to be mistaken for my nemesis in a clever plastic disguise. Still—” he mused. There was fear in Winnie’s expression. “—I really ought to be consistent in my declarations.” Then he shook his head. “No, Ms. Morales, I won’t slaughter you where you stand. The memory of your performance is punishment enough.”

He stalked away, spun on his heel, walked back. “I have an idea. It had occurred to me that if the least funny of you weren’t the Batman, what I might do is to follow the maxim of my old mercenary friends and simply kill you all and let God sort you out.” I knew I was looking death in the distorted, grinning face.

“No,” said the Joker. “One more chance. I must be mellowing.” He chuckled, a horrible sound like a gerbil being pulled under the water and gargling as it drowned. “Yes, a chance. I’m going to extinguish the lights. When I bring them up again, I expect to see a clear sign that one of you is the Batman. I realize there is no phone booth—” He smirked. “Oh, yes, that’s our other good friend. But you get the point.” The Joker raised his hand. “All right, are you ready?” All of us sort of looked at each other. “If anyone tries anything funny, so to speak, my men will rake both the stage and the theater auditorium with automatic fire.” I wondered if we’d all remembered our twine-bound, butcher paper-wrapped parcels.

“Now,” said the Joker.

The lights went out.

Did you ever see Spartacus? There’s that great scene where the Romans order the rebellious slave army to give up their leader and then first one, then another, and eventually every slave there proclaims, “I am Spartacus.”

I thought of that when the lights came up.

You see, we were all—all eighteen of us—the Batman.

I’d worn the costume from the package Bruce had given us under my clothing, as I guessed the rest had, too. In the sudden darkness, I’d struggled out of my street clothes, unfurled the thin cape from under my collar, and pulled the cowl over my head. I had donned the rest of the gear.

So here we were in the glare of the house lights. Eighteen Batpersons: white, black, brown, yellow, male, female, fit, paunchy, young, middle-aged. We were a sight.

The Joker stared at us. With some satisfaction, I saw there was genuine surprise on his face. Then he began to laugh.

I don’t think it was wholly because we were all dressed in Bat-attire. It may have had something to do with the fact that all of us wore Groucho glasses, the heavy black-rimmed kind with the attached big rubber noses and bushy moustaches.

While we stood there waiting for summary execution, the Joker giggled, then chortled, finally whooped with merriment. Tears, or at least something viscous, dripped from his eyes. I thought the ends of his grin would meet around the back of his head.

When he finally could speak, he said, “Perfect. Absolutely perfect. Better than I’d ever hoped.” He burst into laughter again.

And then he let us go.

It was that abrupt. The Joker made some hand motions. Smoke rolled across the stage. Blinding lights flashed. Choking, we fell to our knees. But then the fumes cleared. They weren’t toxic.

The Joker was gone, along with his men.

I felt a strong arm help me to my feet. Bruce. He set his hand on my shoulder and steadied me.

It had been one hell of a show. You might say we’d knocked the audience dead.

Just kidding.

I’ve had a lot of time to think about that night. I’m in law school now—no more Burger Biggie, and no more suggestions of seminary from Uncle Louis.

I still do some stand-up comedy, but there isn’t a hell of a lot of time. In such clubs as I still play, I’ve never again seen Bruce.

About that night . . . I remember how I always used to think I only came truly alive at night, when I could change into somebody different from who I was in the sunlight, somebody more powerful, someone who could move people to react.

I mean, I’m no dummy. I can put two and two together. After what I’ve been through, there ain’t nothing that seems unlikely now.

The newspapers really did a number on what happened at the Aladdin Theater and the joke-off. The writers speculated about why the Joker hadn’t simply triggered a massacre. The consensus seemed to be that the big J must be entering some new phase of his “humor,” something seriously weird, maybe absurdist or the surreal.

Me, I’ve got a different idea. Maybe somebody just got a little bored. No, check that. Seriously bored. And maybe somebody decided that the lack in his life was his opponent.

He decided his antagonist had one crucial shortcoming—no sense of humor. Or at least one so rudimentary it needed a little jarring loose to set it in gear.

A worthy villain needs an equally worthy antagonist.

Just speculation, folks.

I keep my theories to myself. See, I figure that one day I’ll return to the night—and when I do, I might just need a friend.